Hisham,
uh question for you, John. Thanks for
the five bucks. Can you please speak a
little about the role of clinical
psychologists in operations and in other
capacities at the CIA? I love that
question.
That's a terrific question. It's a
little bit sensitive.
So, there are, as you might guess, there
are a lot
of psychologists at the CIA. A lot.
A small number of them, just a few
little
uh are assigned to the Office of Medical
Services, OMS.
And they are there to make sure that the
people the CIA sends overseas are not
crazy.
A lot of them are. You'd be surprised.
And then they're they're
put on a travel ban until they're less
crazy.
Um
But most of the clinical psychologists
at the CIA are split into intelligence
and operations. The intelligence ones
work with the analysts to do
psychological evaluations on foreign
leaders, right?
How we can then use
the psychology of foreign leaders to
get a leg up.
Whether it's in, you know, trade
negotiations or, you know, issues of war
and peace or whatever.
The other ones are in operations. I
worked very closely with the CIA's team
of operational psychologists.
Um
because, let's say
I'm recruiting
a terrorist.
Uh I want to make sure that the guy's
not nuts, that we're not going to use
him in an operation and he's going to
turn around and kill me in the middle of
the operation. Mhm. Or make sure that he
didn't make the whole thing up.
And when he when he volunteered to us
that he was a member of XYZ terrorist
group. I did
I did one operation. I've told the story
a couple of times. It was with a
psychologist and a hypnotist who was a
psychiatrist.
And they hypnotized this guy. I won't
get into the story here, but oh my god,
I've never seen anything like it in my
life. And I've spoken about it a number
of times.
But, um sometimes you need a
psychologist to advise you as to just
how far you can push a guy
before he cracks.
Maybe you want him to crack. Maybe you
want to ruin his life cuz he's an
[__] or he's a double agent or he's a
plant or whatever.
Or maybe you want to push him so he
gives you as much information as he can,
but you don't want him to crack. You
don't want him
to ruin his life.
So, it's
you you find yourself becoming very
close to the psychologist. There were a
couple who were my go-to. Two psychol-
two psychologists who were my go-to
partners on these operations, a man and
a woman. And um I still think about them
all these years later. I
I don't even know if they're still
alive. They probably aren't. But, um
but yeah, you you end up becoming very
close to to the psychologists. John, how
how did torture affect morale in the CIA
while you couldn't while you couldn't
keep with it, I guess, tolerate it. Uh
how did your other colleagues look at it
at the moment and years later? How does
it look in retrospect? It's a good
question. That's a very good question.
Uh in the beginning, the compartment was
so tightly controlled that nobody knew
that this tiny band of of officers was
torturing people.
Nobody knew until um
I'm going to say
six or eight months after the torture
began.
Uh it affected morale.
It split morale.
There there were a lot of guys who were
true believers that not only was this
something that we should be doing, they
were enjoying doing it.
And then, um
and then by 2005,
enough people knew about it and objected
to it that George Tenet pulled back.
So, they were torturing people from
August of 2002 until the middle of 2005.
But they kept the secret prisons going
and they kept while there wasn't like
active
torture in the secret prisons after
2005, there was active torture at
Guantanamo.
>> [clears throat]
>> And um more and more people objected as
more and more people became informed. It
It split morale. It damaged morale. Uh
Sodden, thanks for the 20 bucks. Happy
New Year, John. We know you've had
issues with your former agency. Yeah.
Uh
can you tell [laughter] us a a few Can
you tell us about your co-workers who
were awesome, who we never really hear
about, like Mike Spann and Bob Baer?
Same question for Ted.
Yeah.
Obviously, I never worked at the agency,
but I guess maybe my question would be
like LA Times or something like that.
Anyway,
I liked most of the people that I worked
with. Most of them were genuinely great
guys, women. They were patriots.
Most of them actually happen to be
Democrats.
And um
all they wanted to do is serve their
country.
But it's like the higher up the chain
you go
the easier it is to lose your mind. Like
there there were there were two guys in
particular who I really really liked
when we were all junior officers
together.
One of them became
um deputy
deputy director of counterterrorism and
then deputy director of the FBI for
counterterrorism.
He became a war criminal. Is what it
was. He was a great guy and then all of
a sudden he's like murdering people with
drones. And then bragging about it. The
other became um
head of the uh
Alec Station, Osama bin Laden unit.
Awesome fun guy, hilarious sense of
humor. And he just became a stone cold
killer.
Um besides those two, most of the people
that I that I rose through the ranks
with were really great great men and
women. I I enjoyed their time. Thanks
for the nine bucks Jacob Decker. Um 999
actually. Um the CIA is notorious for
putting people into power that they
want. Do you think they were involved in
Mondani winning in New York? What would
be the objective of having a Muslim
mayor in New York and London?
No.
It's that's just not something that the
CIA is involved in.
No. And you know the CIA
there's a position in the in the NYPD.
It's deputy deputy
police commissioner for intelligence.
And that traditionally goes to
a person coming out of the CIA. Right,
the first one was Dave Cohen. He was the
the deputy director of the CIA for
operations. He retired, he became deputy
commissioner for intelligence. So the
CIA likes things just the way they are.
It doesn't matter who happens to be the
mayor so long as they get their position
and can liaise with the joint terrorism
task force. That's all they care about.
John, let me ask you a really highly
theoretical question. So if let's say we
had uh President Mondani uh and and red
and yellow bunting all over the country
and hammer and sickle flags
if the CIA if the CIA remained in power,
would the CIA basically dutifully
continue to operate under a new
left-wing regime or would that just be
too much for them?
I'm going to give you a
two-pronged like a forked answer.
Uh on the on the one hand
most of the CIA would continue to
operate as if nothing happened because
the the president is the chief
executive.
They serve at the pleasure of the
president. With that said, I think there
would be elements of the CIA's
directorate of operations that would
actively seek to remove a president like
that.
Wow.
I mean John Kennedy was a Cold War
Democratic hawk, anti-communist.
>> War hero.
Yeah. And uh
that didn't save him.
>> [music]
[music]